A Guide to the Virginia Auditor of Public Accounts - Runaway and Escaped Slaves Records, 1794-1863
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
A Guide to the Virginia Auditor of Public Accounts - Runaway and Escaped Slaves Records, 1794-1863
The Library of Virginia
APA 759
1 cu. ft. (2 boxes)
Virginia Auditor of Public Accounts (1776-1928)
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Transferred from the Auditor of Public Accounts in 1913.
Biographical Information
During the antebellum period the General Assembly passed increasingly restrictive laws in response to white fears of slave crime and insurrection. Procedures were established to compensate slaveholders for the loss of their property when slaves ran away or were imprisoned or executed. Some condemned slaves were transported beyond the state's boundaries, frequently to Africa.
Free blacks, too, were subjected to harsh laws intended to persuade or compel them to leave Virginia. Special taxes were assessed against them, emigration to Liberia was promoted, and reenslavement for debt or crime was threatened constantly. Some free blacks did leave, but most stayed despite the restrictions.
Runaway slaves who were captured and whose owners could not be found became the property of the state and were sold to new owners. Localities were reimbursed for the expenses of confining and feeding the slaves until they were sold.
Scope and Content
The Runaway and Escaped Slaves Records, 1794-1863, are housed in two boxes and arranged chronologically, with oversize material in box 2.
Contents List
- 1794, 1806-1817 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- 1820-1823 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- 1824-1827 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- 1828-1829 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- 1830-1832 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- 1833-1835 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- 1836-1840 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- 1841-1849 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- 1850-1859 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- 1861-1863 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Oversize Counties A-B, 1823, 1861-1863. (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Oversize Counties C, 1861-1863. (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Oversize Counties D-E, 1861-1863. (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Oversize Counties G-H, 1861-1863. (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Oversize Counties L-N, 1861-1863. (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Oversize Counties O-P, 1861-1863. (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Oversize Counties R-T, 1861-1863. (Box 2, Folder 7)